<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>BCCP</title><link>http://bccp.berkeley.edu/</link><description>Berkeley Center for Cosmological Physics</description><atom:link href="http://bccp.berkeley.edu/rss.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 02:01:24 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>BCCP Workshop held in January 2014</title><link>http://bccp.berkeley.edu/news/bccp-workshop-jan-2014/</link><dc:creator>BCCP</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;BCCP and the Instituto Avanzado de Cosmologia Mexico held the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bccp.berkeley.edu/beach_program/index2014.html"&gt;5th
annual Essential Cosmology for the Next Generation Meeting&lt;/a&gt; January
13-17, 2014, popularly known as Cosmology on the Beach. The conference
blends a winter school of lecture courses by world-leading scholars
with plenary talks on hot research topics. This year, topics included
CMB polarization, gravitational wave cosmology, particle physics,
tests of gravity, and statistical and experimental methods. For slides
from the BCCP/IAC meeting Essential Cosmology for the Next Generation
2014 workshop, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bccp.berkeley.edu/beach_program/index2014.html"&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;. They are
also available on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bccp.berkeley.edu/beach_program/COTB14presentations.html"&gt;Presentations Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>http://bccp.berkeley.edu/news/bccp-workshop-jan-2014/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2014 08:33:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>BigBOSS Gets a Kick-Start From the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation</title><link>http://bccp.berkeley.edu/news/big-boss-kickstart/</link><dc:creator>BCCP</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img alt="/images/posts/Instruments-and-Mayall-by-Mark-Duggan1.jpg" class="align-left" src="http://bccp.berkeley.edu/images/posts/Instruments-and-Mayall-by-Mark-Duggan1.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A $2.1 million grant from the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moore.org/newsitem.aspx?id=4812"&gt;Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation&lt;/a&gt; to the University of
California at Berkeley, through the Berkeley Center for Cosmological
Physics (BCCP), will fund the development of revolutionary
technologies for BigBOSS, a project now in the proposal stage designed
to study dark energy with unprecedented precision. BigBOSS is based at
the U.S. Department of Energy’s Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory
(Berkeley Lab).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“BigBOSS is the next big thing in cosmology,” says Uroš Seljak,
Director of the BCCP, who is a professor of physics and astronomy at
UC Berkeley and a member of Berkeley Lab’s Physics Division. “It would
map millions and millions of galaxies, allowing us to measure dark
energy to high precision – and would yield other important scientific
results as well, including determining neutrino mass and the number of
neutrino families.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dark energy is the unknown something that appears to account for
almost three-quarters of the mass-energy of the universe and is the
cause of its accelerating expansion. The discovery of the accelerating
universe, announced in 1998 by two teams, resulted in the 2011 Nobel
Prize in Physics, divided between Berkeley Lab and UC Berkeley
astrophysicist Saul Perlmutter, leader of the Supernova Cosmology
Project, and Brian Schmidt and Adam Riess of the competing High‑z
Supernova Search team. “After we won the Nobel Prize, the question we
all heard most was, ‘Now that you’ve discovered dark energy, what
comes next?’” says Perlmutter, who is the Executive Director of the
BCCP as well as principal investigator for the Moore Foundation’s
BigBOSS grant. “The answer is pretty clear: we have to find out what
dark energy is. There’s no end of theories. To know which are
possible, what we need most is the kind of accurate observational
evidence that only BigBOSS and other advanced experiments can give
us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://newscenter.lbl.gov/news-releases/2012/12/04/moore-foundation-bigboss/"&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://bccp.berkeley.edu/news/big-boss-kickstart/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Dec 2012 21:00:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Scientists Measure the Reionization of the Early Universe</title><link>http://bccp.berkeley.edu/news/spt-reionization.rst/</link><dc:creator>BCCP</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img alt="/images/posts/SPTsky350.jpg" class="align-left" src="http://bccp.berkeley.edu/images/posts/SPTsky350.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New data from the South Pole Telescope indicates that the birth of the
first massive galaxies that lit up the early universe was an explosive
event, happening faster and ending sooner than suspected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extremely bright, active galaxies formed and fully illuminated the
universe by the time it was 750 million years old, or about 13 billion
years ago, according to Oliver Zahn, a postdoctoral fellow at the
Berkeley Center for Cosmological Physics (BCCP) at the University of
California, Berkeley, who led the data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://bccp.berkeley.edu/news/spt-reionization.rst/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2012 21:07:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Looking to the Skies: Modern Cosmology and the Maya</title><link>http://bccp.berkeley.edu/news/looking-to-the-skies/</link><dc:creator>BCCP</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fwtQpsUrI8I" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen style="float:left;margin:20px;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this video, Berkeley Lab astrophysicists and Nobel laureates,
George Smoot and Saul Perlmutter -- joined by Berkeley Lab physicist
Eric Linder and UC anthropologist Gerardo Aldana -- explore the
cultural and scientific connections between Mayan astronomers and
modern cosmologists as they look to the skies for answers to how the
universe evolved, how it might end, and our place in it. The
fundamental human curiosity about our origins and fate, a quest that
persists across time and cultures, has been enriched by recent
discoveries about dark energy, the Big Bang, and the accelerating
universe. New knowledge has only increased our sense of wonder about
the cosmos and deepened our appreciation for what the Mayans achieved
using only the naked eye.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://bccp.berkeley.edu/news/looking-to-the-skies/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 18:03:56 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>